<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Personal | Amy Palamountain]]></title>
  <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-22T12:10:58+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Amy Palamountain]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dealing to power-plays]]></title>
    <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/2012/12/22/how-do-we-deal-with-sexist-power-plays/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/2012/12/22/how-do-we-deal-with-sexist-power-plays</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1></h1>

<p>To be honest with you, I have thought about writing a post to this effect on and off for a very long time. The thoughts that have prevented me from posting on this topic have roots in fear. Fear of the impression I will make on people, fear of people thinking that I’m just a talker not a doer. Fear of people taking me the wrong way.</p>

<p>And then Iris Classon <a href="http://www.irisclasson.com/2012/12/19/stupid-question-107-shhh-harassment-not-a-problem-strong-content-warning/">posted about 2 horrible men who disgraced</a><a href="http://www.irisclasson.com/2012/12/19/stupid-question-107-shhh-harassment-not-a-problem-strong-content-warning/"> themselves beyond belief</a>, making a wonderful person feel uncomfortable and revolting. She took a very bold step and made her experiences public. She wasn’t afraid to speak up and show everyone this kind of behaviour is not to be tolerated . In every way this is the appropriate course of action. If these men knew what they were doing – these men deserved to be disgraced. These men deserve their reputation to be spoilt. If they are disturbed individuals, then they need our help.</p>

<p>Disclaimer: If you are a man, I have one thing to say to you. You <strong>DO NOT</strong> deserve to feel disgraced or embarrassed to be a man in light of to what happened to Iris. You do not need to feel shame in any way. These are actions by individuals who truly are not of a safe mental capacity to be taking part in any community. You should not shoulder any feelings of shame. You are awesome.</p>

<p>What happened to Iris, is an example of ‘Power Play’ behaviours. At the core, power plays  have a net effect of making one person feel strong, powerful and dominant  at the expense of another feeling weak, powerless and even fearful. They are about bolstering one ego, while tearing down another.</p>

<p>Groping a woman at a conference says very plainly ‘ I am entitled to you, and you are not entitled to say no’. This is a power play. Humiliating a peer about their lack of knowledge in a particular subject is a power play, its says  ’ your contribution is meaningless because I know more than you’. Consistently talking about colleagues/friends breasts is a power play of the most obnoxious kind – it says ‘ I am more important and powerful than all the woman here’.</p>

<p>I think in general, power play behaviour can be divided into two broad categories – those that are conscious, and those that are not. These should be dealt with in different ways.</p>

<p>What Iris has had to endure is an example of a conscious power play. These ‘men’ feel threatened by Iris, a woman who is strong, clever and well liked. These ‘men’ felt so threatened by this that they felt the need to launch a personal attack. To ‘put her in her place’. To assert their dominance. To assert to themselves that they are important, and somehow relevant. What they did was designed to make Iris feel frightened and unsure about her position - luckily Iris is as strong as she is and told them where to go. Not all would be strong enough to do this. This kind of calculated power play is extremely dangerous. Outwardly hostile and threatening power plays <strong>need</strong> to be reported to the police.</p>

<p>There is a second kind of power play – the unconscious kind. These are usually subtle, off the cuff comments and actions. Putting someone down in front of your peers. Assuming that the only woman in the meeting should take notes. Relentlessly questioning a woman about why she wore a dress and make up ‘ who are you going out with?’. In all of these cases someone is unconsciously putting another ‘in their place’ in the pecking order.</p>

<p>Most of the time, off the cuff comments like this are easily rectified with a quick apology. Sometimes though a comment is made without the person being aware of the impact it had on another person. Most people out there mean well, so we should give people the benefit of the doubt in these cases.  By this is defiantly don’t mean ‘let it slide’ I just mean, don’t assume the person is a nut case (unless of course, they are)</p>

<p><strong>We shouldn’t let these unconscious power plays slide.</strong> Making people aware of the hurtful and uncomfortable things they said or did, is the only way forward. I’m not talking rage induced table flips. Just a quiet word or two which makes the person think about the reasons why the said that statement.</p>

<ul>
<li>I don’t get it? Whats so funny about ….</li>
<li>Can you please explain what you mean?</li>
<li>Of what concern is it to you if I wear a dress?</li>
<li>Do you realise you sound incredibly sexist? I’m sure your not, so just wondering if you ment that?</li>
</ul>


<p>It’s not the words, it’s the effect of the words, gently guide the person to realise that what they said was embarrassing to their character. Make them understand that you know that they are not a ‘douche bag’ but in that moment, they really sounded like one.</p>

<p>Now – easier said than done right? I know <strong>so many</strong> strong woman, all with stories to tell around sexist comments or actions. Almost none of these stories end with the woman standing up for her self. The ones that do? Not many of these end pretty. ‘Lighten Up’, “It was a joke sweetheart’ ‘ Your mental’ ‘But all I was saying is I like your tits’.</p>

<p>When challenging someone on a comment, generally most people will be so embarrassed, will be unwilling to admit their failing and instead of apologising  they will attempt to ensure that they remain on top – essentially a continuation of the original power play.</p>

<p>This is where we all need to pitch in. We need to <strong>ALL</strong> start recognising these behaviours, and help those in need, in their time of need. If you see someone shrinking unnecessarily as a result of someones words or actions. <strong>Step up!</strong> Gently make them understand that they currently look like a worse person than they actually are. It takes two seconds, and doesn’t have to cause any confrontation. If the person gets worked up over it? Who cares. Let them stew on it. Eventually your words will sink in.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/be-excelent.jpeg"></p>

<p>These days most of us agree that treating each other with respect, is the only way to live. Yet sometimes we stand by, and stay quiet when we see others not living by this code. Iris said in her post that so many woman keep quiet. It’s because they don’t realise the support they would have if they spoke up. If we start standing up for sexism in the moment, all of these issues will follow suit. Woman, transgender, or in fact any minority will start to feel supported and listened to, and people will generally learn to be even more excellent to each other!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Amy Grenade]]></title>
    <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/11/22/the-amy-grenade/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-22T00:00:00+13:00</updated>
    <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/11/22/the-amy-grenade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been almost 4 weeks since I had my cast off and my pins removed, and life has immeasurably improved.</p>

<p>It wasn’t without hiccup though. The day the ‘Amy grenade’ was pulled, the first thing the surgeon said was “your fingers are swollen” I explained that they did that from time to time, if i used them too much. He removed my cast and set free my skinny corpse arm. Even with swelling it was obviously wasted. It felt so vulnerable, like it would snap at any minute. It had had a 13 months of utter under use due to pain, and 2 months complete immobilisation. Needless to say my muscles had receded to a surface area not dissimilar to to that of a deflated balloon.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/the-amy-grenade/wrist.jpg"></p>

<p>Then he found a pair of regular pliers and pulled at the pins. The best I can describe the feeling was like a pressure build up that moved through my wrist as each pin was pulled. Like a fishing net that picks up more debris as its being dragged through water. It didn’t hurt during though there was a deep ache after, but it was no worse than anything I had experienced to date. It did give me the shakes though, just shock I guess. I have a 17 second video that captures the moment, that’s how quick it was! I have never felt anything like it in my entire life, and hope never to again.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/LDJu8g05gZM "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Unfortunately the surgeon was not happy with the level of swelling, the colour, or the temperature – dead cold. He explained that sometimes after extensive and prolonged injury the nervous system can ‘wind it self up’. The pain sensation pathway involves a collection of chemicals being released from one cell to the next, transmitting the signals required to correctly respond to pain and trauma. Normally this pathway completes on its own accord, but under some conditions an infinite loop is achieved. Long after injury has healed ,the pain pathway is still responding as though there is still trauma. Resulting in swelling, inflammation, temperature changes, heightened skin sensitivity and of course – pain. The surgeon reefer me on to a pain specialist,who also so had to be my anaesthetist. I saw him a few weeks after and he diagnosed it as Complex Region Pain Syndrome Type 1. He was happy that it was only minor and seemed to be receding on its own, apparently my constant massaging was helping restore normal responses. He gave me some cream which apparently releases chemicals which help break the feedback loop and sent me on my way.</p>

<p>The first few days were, to be frank, terrifying. But over the last 4 weeks the improvements are already huge. I have 45 degrees of upward flexion and 30 degrees downward. I can flex upward with a 1kg weight with no pain at all. My fingers and thumb move freely and without pain. My grip feels stronger than I remembered – though its still measures just less than my non dominate hand. Rome wasn’t built in a day, and I have many more months of rehabilitation. In the short term, my goals are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Push myself up from my chair.</li>
<li>Hold a 2kg weight in my hand with my elbow on a table, arm vertical. Without shaking like a leaf.</li>
<li>Improve my grip strength beyond that of my left.</li>
</ul>


<p>Even without anymore rehabilitation, the results as they stand today have changed my life. I can open doors, I can dress, I can write and BEST of all I can type. All without pain. Initially I would fatigue due to the weakness in my fingers, hand wrist and arm. Yesterday worked for 7 hours without once getting sore! I coded for almost 7 hours, without getting sore! Not once! Not a niggle or a pull. My head tapped out before my hand did. I am for the first time in a long time, starting to once again feel effective in my job and hobbies. I can get into that zone of deep concentration again – something I have not had the privilege of doing for over a year.
 </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wrist Reconstruction]]></title>
    <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/09/07/wrist-reconstruction/"/>
    <updated>2011-09-07T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/09/07/wrist-reconstruction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two weeks ago I went into hospital to finally get the reconstruction of my right wrist I have been waiting for. No nerves this time – I knew what to expect, was well researched and it was going to get rid of my pain. I closed my eyes in theater and opened them a second later in recovery. What I didn’t expect was the pain. I guess being cut, sawed, screwed and pined will do that to you. The surgeon had warned me how painful it was but I really was not prepared. It took a fair whack of Morphine to bring it down to a bearable level and Tramadol (synthetic opiate) to bring it down to a dull ache.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/wrist-reconstruction/bandage.jpeg"></p>

<p>They had cast me in a back slab. A kind of half cast and bandage. When the swelling started coming down after about a week it became loose and would often push on my pins (which stick out the skin). This really hurts. The first night was impossible to sleep, pain was intense and anesthetic sickness kept my head in a bowl for the evening. Unfortunately I have had to keep taking Tramadol much to my distaste. I wouldn’t cope well without it. I said in my last post I wanted to be off the Tramadol by week 2, due to how either sick or euphoric i feel. Doing good though, some days I only take one (down from 6 a day)</p>

<p>Its now two weeks on and I have had my first dressing change. It looked a lot better than I was expecting. The cut is so clean and straight – even if the photo doesn’t do it justice. Its about 4 inches right down the middle of the wrist.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/posts/wrist-reconstruction/wound.jpg"></p>

<p>Once opened the surgeon was able to use what was left of my Scapholunate ligament to tighten the gap between my Scaphoid and Lunate bones. He corrected the orientation of the Scaphoid then screwed a bone anchor into my Lunate bone, and passed the remainder of the ligament through the anchor. This is lucky because if there had not been enough ligament left then the surgeon would have made a similar length incision on the underside of my wrist to harvest a ligament from my forearm. Once fastened he inserted two wire pins into the side of my wrist to hold everything in place while it heals. No I am not going to see if they are conductive and can light up a bulb !</p>

<p>In 6 weeks I will return to the surgeon for a quick pin removal – which yes – I intend to film. Then its off to the hand therapist for what sounds like an intense program. At this point I may be able to return to work half time 4 weeks ahead of his original 3 month medical certificate!!!</p>

<p>All of this is just so positive, I am well on my way through my 12 month recovery. Typing with two hands, picking up light things, gripping and dressing myself. Eventually Judo and weights, and finally back to the mountain</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A visit to the surgeon.]]></title>
    <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/06/02/a-visit-to-the-surgeon/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-02T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/06/02/a-visit-to-the-surgeon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have seen the surgeon for my follow up appointment. The bandage is off and the stitches are out. I have two small cuts from where the probe went in. Pain at this point is back to where it was previously, and any additional pain must just be scarring tissue. So doing quite well.</p>

<p>We discussed exactly what he saw during the Arthroscopy and what is required to be done.</p>

<p><strong>It boils down to two choices</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Do nothing. Cope with the pain as it is now. In 5 – 10 years it will have developed into chronic arthritis. The range of motion in my wrist will be almost nothing. I risk requiring a full wrist fusion to relieve pain.</li>
<li>Surgical intervention. This involves a large incision over the top of my wrist. A small hole is drilled into each of the Scaphoid and Lunate bones. Metal bone anchors are placed into each hole and a tendon harvested from the other side of my wrist (another large incision) is threaded through each anchor. Wires and placed to help the tendon graft in place correctly. Basically a knee reconstruction in a finer scale, with massive wounds.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Q and A with the surgeon. </strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Grade of tear and degree of instability – Grade III ( of IV) with no gross instability. Good news!</li>
<li>Expected progression with no surgery – see above.</li>
<li>Recovery time if surgery/ progression – 3 Months in a cast. Wires are removed as an outpatient procedure. 6 months physical therapy before resuming normal activities with weight more than 5kg and sports.</li>
<li>Surgeons experience – Specialist hand surgeon. Last procedure of this kind was 2 weeks ago.</li>
<li>Any lost movement – Some extension and flexion will be lost. I may never do a press up again.</li>
<li>Any further surgery – No surgery comes with a money back guarantee, basically no comment.</li>
<li>Arthritis – Possible.</li>
<li>Surgeons question for me was – is changing jobs an option? I fired back with would he want to give up his job (he is very passionate very talented surgeon). Being a programmer is my lively hood. I will NOT give it up this early in the game.</li>
</ul>


<p>To me this is a no brainer, I am having the surgery. I have read around quite a lot and feel very informed about this procedure (Google books for Orthopedic Surgery text books for the win). I have also read about peoples experiences with this injury. Pain after the surgery sounds quite bad, the surgeon warned me of this and told me that his last patient was still eating Tramadol two weeks on. But he’s a silly boy and I am way tougher than any silly boy ! I really hope I can be tougher – Tramadol is no fun, I am either asleep all day or completely out of my head.</p>

<p>As for long term recovery – I have read many journal articles which give numbers which indicate perhaps 80% of people have good to excellent results and are completely pain free. Great news for me because I WILL be in that 80%. Determination and common sense should be all I need to ensure this.</p>

<p>These are the <strong>activities</strong> I would like to be able to do <strong>pain free within a year</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Use a keyboard and a mouse for long periods without pain (i.e get my life back)</li>
<li>Pressing or gripping down while moving – activities like doing the dishes/ pulling pants up.</li>
<li>Writing</li>
<li>Be back at Judo – readjust my technique to be left handed.</li>
</ul>


<p>Stay tuned – Once I have heard from ACC (~3 weeks) I should shortly after get a date for surgery. I hope to be on the table as soon as possible. Hopefully within 2 months. The sooner I can get this done – the sooner I am on my path to getting back to normal.</p>

<p> </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Right wrist &#8211; Scapolunate troubles.]]></title>
    <link href="http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/05/26/right-wrist-scapolunate-troubles/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-26T00:00:00+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://amy.palamounta.in/2011/05/26/right-wrist-scapolunate-troubles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Its been ten months since I broke my Scaphoid, but I am only at the starting line on the race to recovery.
A group of us decided to hit the mountain for a weekend in July 2010. It was my first time snow boarding, and I was having a great time. Really starting to get the nack of it. I was boarding down at reasonable speed, turned a corner straight onto a wide steep area of ice. Picking up speed too quickly I panicd and dug my heals in. I smashed the end of my Scaphoid on the way down (see the pretty bright spot on the right? that’s apparently the break)</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/scapholunate-trouble/mri-break.png"></p>

<p>Prof. Allan Thurston. He explained to me that there are three ligaments which serve the purpose of unifying the movement of the Scaphoid and the Lunate bones during normal wrist movement. He predicted that the that the top and the middle ligament were probably damaged. We proceeded with arranging a diagnostic Arthroscopy of my wrist.</p>

<p>I was out for 15 minutes under General. It was quite an interesting experience, I was fairly nervous and jittery The nurses were lovely and gave me warmed blankets. It calms you quite a bit really. I went in to the operating room. Moved onto the table, and then everyone got to work around me. I remember the nurse saying “you will feel it coming over you now, like a drink” and it did. It got dark from the left hand side and I tasted something funny “I have a funny taste in my mouth” and then I was gone.</p>

<p>Just like that. Woke up like nothing happened in recovery room. I felt great to. I was so happy and foggy, I couldn’t stop saying “Thank you”. I think it was enjoyable only because I was out for 15 minutes – not enough time to start feeling bad.</p>

<p>Prof came to see me and said he went right in over the joint. He expected there to be obstruction but there was not. His guess was correct at least two of my ligaments were completely severed. He wouldn’t discuss as I was still high as a kite on the anesthetic, but said we would need to do something about it. If we don’t it will follow a very predictable and chronic degeneration pattern, causing my right hand to be essentially a dead weight at the end of my arm. No more programming, no more picking things up, no more right hand.</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/posts/scapholunate-trouble/gap.jpg"></p>

<p>Next week I see him to discuss the options. I have done a lot of research and know that K wires and a reconstruction are pretty likely. It sounds similar to a knee reconstruction. I will keep blogging about my recovery, it will be a good motivator for me to keep track of my progress in the coming months. If there is one thing I would like you to take home, your hands and your wrists are a huge asset to you, coder or not. So look after them.
 </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
